Back in undergrad I taught in high school
for a few months.
There was a proof I liked to show my students,
because it surprised most of them.
This was the setup: every student knows that
you can't sum fractions element-wise.
What many students don't know is that you
*can*, actually, as long as long you're just
trying to prove an inequality.
My main line of research is doing proofs with
Coq, so let me share a Coq proof of this inequality.
That's it.
You can check that the statement at the top
matches what I wanted to prove, and there's
a Qed at the end, and I promise that Coq actually
accepts this, so… all good?
Hey, I can even add a little rooster next
to the proof to make it more convincing!
If this were a live talk I'd pause and ask
people to raise their hands if they feel they
understand this proof.
But since I'm alone at home talking to my
camera instead, I'll just assume that you're
like me, and that you don't find this pile
of tactics particularly enlightening.
What are you supposed to do?
Simulate Coq's tactic engine in your mind
to understand what's going on?
What we're looking at together is not what
mathematicians typically call “a proof”,
because it's missing the proof states, which
Coq calls “goals”.
What we're looking at is a proof *script*:
a Coq program that records the steps that
establish that a theorem holds.
It's made of a sequence of tactics, each of
which correspond to a small amount of progress
in the proof, like multiplying both sides
of an inequality by a positive number or reasoning
by induction.
What it does not record are the “goals”,
the intermediate proof states that these steps
lead to.
That's because, if you run the proof script
in a Coq development environment, goals are
automatically computed and displayed by Coq
itself.
The downside is that this makes it nigh impossible
to understand a proof script on its own, without
running it.
In many cases we don't really care why a theorem
is true, so it does not matter that the proof
script is inscrutable.
Maybe I'm proving that a particular program
does not perform out-of-bounds array accesses,
for example, and it's enough for me to know
that the theorem holds.
In those cases, if Coq is happy, I'm happy
too.
But sometimes proofs do carry interesting
insight.
Maybe there's a particularly tricky case that
I'd like readers to think about, or maybe
I'm using Coq proofs to communicate interesting
mathematical ideas, or maybe I'm teaching
students about simple math and logic concepts
and using the computer to support my explanations
and introduce formal reasoning.
In those cases I want to show the reader what
steps we took, and what states they led to.
That's easy to do in Coq if the readers have
access to Coq: they can just feed the proof
script to Coq in an interactive IDE and inspect
the intermediate states that Coq computes
and displays.
But maybe your readers don't have the right
version of Coq installed.
Or maybe your proof has large dependencies
that take a while to compile and your readers
are just browsing casually.
Maybe they're on a mobile phone.
Maybe you're writing a book and, well, your
readers can't run Coq on a physical book.
So what do people do to write manuals, tutorials,
textbooks, blog posts, or any other piece
of text that mixes Coq proofs and prose?
In most cases they do something like this:
they run the proof in Coq and then, by hand,
they copy the output of each tactic into source
code comments.
Here's what it looks like in Certified Programming
with Dependent Types.
Here's what it looks like in Illya's Programs
and Proofs.
Here's what it looks like in Software Foundations.
This is a particularly cumbersome process.
It takes a lot of work; it's easy to make
mistakes; and it's very easy to forget to
update the comments after changing a proof
script.
There's also no way to check whether the comments
are still valid, so you have to rely on readers
to point issues as they discover them.
There's got to be a better way, and that's
where Alectryon comes in.
Alectryon is two things: first, it's a compiler
that records Coq's output and embeds it within
the proof script to create interactive proof
visualizations, and second it's a literate
programming system for Coq.
Here's that same proof as rendered by Alectryon.
Alectryon's compiler took the input Coq file,
fed it to Coq, collected the output, formatted
it, and generated a webpage interleaving inputs
and outputs.
So what you're looking at is an interactive
webpage: each input fragment of the original
Coq script is a button that you can hover
on or click to show or hide the corresponding
proof state, along with any accompanying messages.
Every time I make changes to the Coq file
I can re-run Alectryon, and it will update
the visualization.
And because all outputs are recorded, browsing
through the proof is instantaneous: there's
no need to load a copy of Coq in your browser.
All of the layout and display is done in CSS,
so you can actually change the rendering in
all sorts of fancy ways.
For example, here's a version that shows the
output on the side.
Here's another version that mimics the usual
interface that you see in a proof assistant,
with the code on the left and the goals and
messages on the right.
Also, since we're now in a web browser, we
can make everything look extra-fancy thanks
to the magic of Coq notations combined with
JavaScript rendering of LaTeX code, and now
I have a much more reasonable shot at getting
you to understand the proof:
First we sum the two fractions on the right;
then we expand the numerator; then we multiply
both sides to get rid of the denominators;
then we simplify and cancel on both sides,
and lastly we use the fact that a square is
always positive.
That's really what it is: you take a Coq document,
you put little annotations to indicate which
parts of the output should be displayed by
default, and then Alectryon does the magic
of running Coq and embedding its answers into
your document.
And here's an example of hiding parts of the
input to show something slightly different:
part of teaching students about Coq involves
explaining the Curry–Howard correspondence
by showing how tactics construct proof terms
under the hood.
In this example, I've added calls to the Coq
command “Show Proof” between each line,
and Alectryon shows the piecemeal construction
of a proof term.
----
Ok, so this solves the problem of displaying
goals and outputs to readers, but that's just
one part of writing a document that includes
Coq proofs: the other part is writing the
explanatory prose that accompanies the proofs.
In fact, if you inspect this example from
CPDT closely, you'll notice that there's no
actual code here — it's all prose in comments!
There's lots and lots of prose around the
code: in fact, there's a whole book in there,
written within source code comments.
I have a lot of respect for the authors of
all these Coq books.
It takes a whole different level of grit and
determination to edit a whole book out of
source code comments, and the books that I
mentioned are some of the best Coq books out
there.
Again, it shouldn't have to be this way.
My text editor has all sorts of nifty features
for editing Markdown or reStructuredText documents,
like smart navigation, spell-checking, live
previews, and convenient shortcuts, so it's
particularly frustrating when I end up having
to write all my code inside Coq comments.
Alectryon has an answer for that as well:
it includes a suite of literate programming
tools for Coq that make it much easier to
create and edit documents that mix prose and
proofs.
The code you're looking at on this screen
is a snippet from a blog post I wrote recently.
When you give Alectryon a Coq file, it can
compile it to a webpage, but it can also generate
a reStructuredText file by partitioning the
Coq sources into a sequence of code and comment
blocks, extracting the comments, and wrapping
each code fragment into a reStructuredText
code block.
This is what it looks like after flipping
the code and the prose around.
The syntax is reStructuredText.
reStructuredText is a great markup language,
very much like Markdown but with a robust
story for writing extensions; in fact, I used
this whole presentation is just one large
Coq file; I used Alectryon to convert it to
reStructuredText.
The best part is that you can go back: once
you're done editing the prose of your document
and you're ready to resume hacking on the
proofs, you can use Alectryon to convert the
reStructuredText file back into a Coq source
file, in which the prose is wrapped in special
comments and the code is at the top level.
Here, let's go back to the original code.
These two transformations are the inverse
of one another, so you can switch between
the code-oriented view and the prose-oriented
view at will.
This is trivial to integrate into an IDE;
I did it for Emacs, and I'm sure it would
be very easy to do in any other editor.
Being able to go back and forth between reStructuredText
and Coq means that Alectryon does not have
to implement its own markup language for literate
comments: it can just piggyback on the existing
reStructuredText toolchain, which is very
robust and used by a lot of people for all
sorts of documents, like the reference manuals
of Python, Agda, Haskell, and a host of other
languages — including Coq.
If you're familiar with literate programming,
you might notice that this is a bit different
from the usual process.
Normally, in systems like WEB or org-mode,
you start with a main document, which you
can either “tangle” to get executable
source code, or “weave” to get a document
suitable for typesetting or reading, like
LaTeX or HTML.
But in most cases, it's not particularly easy
to edit the generated code and mirror these
edits back into the original sources.
It does not matter too much for regular programming
languages, although it does make it trickier
to use tools like linters or debuggers.
But for a Coq proof, you really want to be
able to step through the proofs interactively
while you're writing them, and that's why
most proof-heavy Coq literature is written
in Coqdoc, with the prose embedded inside
comments.
So that's what Alectryon does: it gives you
bidirectional editing, which allows you to
toggle between code and prose seamlessly,
so you're free to use the most appropriate
editing environment at all times.
Importantly, there's no preferred view of
a document: you can pick either the reStructuredText
view or the Coq view as the one you store
and distribute.
For a literate Coq library you would probably
distribute the code-oriented view so that
users can compile your files as regular Coq
sources without having to know anything about
Alectryon, and for a book with a few Coq examples
you might distribute reStructuredText files
instead.
----
Now that I've given you a sense of what Alectryon
does, let me say a bit about how it does it.
Alectryon is a Python program, and it's written
as a collection of mostly independent modules:
- A “core” module handles communication
with Coq through the SerAPI protocol.
An interesting technical challenge is sentence
segmentation: Coq's notation system makes
it almost impossible to determine where a
Coq sentence starts or ends, so we use Coq's
APIs directly for this.
- A “transforms” module improves the rendering
of the results and processes display annotations
that specify which parts of the output to
show or hide by default.
This module can accommodate user-specified
transforms, which make it possible to special-case
the rendering of certain types or constructs
and generally customize the output (as an
alternative, you can also customize the output
by running JavaScript directly in the browser).
Here are two concrete examples: in this first
one, I'm trying to get a better sense of the
internal workings of Coq's red-black trees,
so I'm progressively adding elements and seeing
how the resulting trees look.
The default output isn't very convincing.
Now here's the same thing, but rendered using
a graph library to display the trees, which
makes it clear how the structure of the trees
is affected by the order in which elements
are added.
In this second example, I have a hypothetical
compiler that takes C code and produces a
binary.
What I've done here is ask Alectryon to take
the bytes printed by Coq; call `objdump` on
them to get an assembly code listing; highlight
*that* using Pygments; and then inline the
result into the output.
- An HTML module translates a recorded Coq
session to HTML; this is mostly straightforward,
though we're doubly careful to produce good
code to make sure that the result works without
JavaScript and looks decent even without CSS;
that's because if you write a blog, for example,
many people will read it through an RSS feed
and these mostly don't support CSS.
- A “literate” module is in charge of
tangling and untangling, from Coq to reStructuredText
and back.
Starting from Coq it's just a matter of identifying
comments, which we do using a recursive descent
parser (it's harder than it looks, because
the rules governing Coq comments and strings
are pretty tricky to get right; so tricky
that it trips up the syntax highlighter that
I'm using for this presentation).
Starting from reST we use the standard reST
parser to delimit sections of code and comments,
and we jump through a few hoops to make indentation
work out.
In both directions we keep track of source
code positions; this makes the process quite
a bit trickier, but it allows us to keep the
position that the user is looking at when
they switch from one view to the other; this
is pretty crucial to ensure a nice experience
when toggling between the code and prose views.
As a bonus, it allows us to run the reStructuredText
syntax checker in the background when the
user is in the Coq view and translate error
positions to display them at the right place
in the Coq view.
- A “docutils” and a “sphinx” modules
plug Alectryon into popular reStructuredText
compilation toolchains to allow users to include
bits of Coq code into larger documents and
compile them with their favorite tools.
----
The paper has a lot of evaluation, and I encourage
you to check it out if you're curious; in
brief, the evaluation is organized around
two axes:
- The first experiment is intended to evaluate
Alectryon's robustness: we've compiled plenty
of documents and Coq libraries, totally tens
of thousands of lines of code and thousands
of printed pages, and the approach seems pretty
robust.
We can compile all of Coq's standard library,
various blog posts, chapters excerpted from
various books, and even a complete volume
from Software Foundations.
If you're familiar with some of the books
I mentioned then you may be wondering how
this actually works, because most of them
are written in Coqdoc, not in reStructuredText,
and I've said before that Alectryon processes
reStructuredText documents.
That's actually a neat example of Alectryon's
extensibility.
What we do for Coqdoc documents, instead of
asking their authors to port them to reStructuredText,
is to render the code and Coq's output with
Alectryon, but we run Coqdoc for the prose
part and we incorporate the HTML that it generates
into the webpages that we produce.
- The second experiment measures Alectryon's
speed.
All the graphs are in the paper, but the long
story short is that Alectryon has a median
overhead of 3x on compilation times (90% of
all files fall below 7x), and a good 1/3 of
that is communication overhead that can probably
be eliminated in the future.
The rest is the overhead of collecting and
formatting goals, which can be pretty costly
for files that have a many goals.
----
It's hard to do justice to all the related
work in this area in just a few minutes, so
I'll simply say that Alectryon builds on decades
of great ideas for making programs and proofs
more understandable, all the way from a paper
in 1980 co-authored by Eric Schmidt and Phil
Wadler to PhD theses written just a year ago.
There's 60 citations and three pages of related
work in the paper; if you're curious about
the history of this stuff, you should really
have a look.
----
To recap, Alectryon provides an architecture
to record and visualize Coq proofs, facilitating
sharing and interactive exploration of proof
scripts; and a bidirectional translator between
woven and tangled documents, enabling seamless
editing of prose and code.
Alectryon is freely available on GitHub, and
it's already used in the wild.
We use it for our group blog, I know someone
is trying to use it for their Coq documentation
at their company, and there's even 3rd-party
packages starting to pop up to integrate it
with other blogging platforms.
I'm sure some day a kind soul will help me
figure out how to put it on OPAM, too.
Or maybe on the Python package index.
Maybe I can conclude with a few words about
the next steps.
Here are some directions that I'm exploring
or would like help exploring.
First, I'd like to make a LaTeX backend: reStructuredText
can produce LaTeX in addition to HTML, so
it would make sense to support that as well.
I have a branch for this, and it's almost
ready.
Second, I'd like to explore advanced visualizations
further.
There are many domains for which the natural
visualization for a piece of data is not text.
I have a few examples in the paper, but I'd
like to push that idea further.
In fact, what would be really neat would be
to settle on a standard for Coq developments
to specify how to render a particular type.
I'm thinking of display-only notations that
would produce images, graphs, plots, etc.
Once we have this, we could even integrate
it with IDEs and finally stop envying the
Racket folks with their magic picture tricks.
Third, for all the machine learning wizards
out there, I'd like to explore automatic proof
summarization — just like automatically
identifying the most exciting moments of a
soccer game, but for Coq proofs.
More formally, the task is to automatically
identify a small subset of proof steps that
lead to particularly interesting or relevant
goals; we'd use this in combination with Alectryon
to identify the most interesting parts of
a proof development.
Finally, I'd like to extend the system to
other languages, both for the markup side
and for the Coq side.
I built Alectryon with Coq and reStructuredText,
but very little of it is actually Coq or reStructuredText
specific.
To port Alectryon to a different language,
like Lean for example, you would need to add
a Python module that invokes Lean and collects
its output, and if you also wanted the literate
programming support you'd want to make a bidirectional
translator for Lean's comment syntax.
The literate programming parts were actually
inspired by work that I did for F* a few years
ago, so adding new languages really shouldn't
be too hard.
If you're interested in getting Alectryon
to work with your favorite proof assistant,
please get in touch.